<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The people and souldiers observations, on the Scotch message to the Parliament, concerning the King; 5. of November 1647. By the scope whereof, all who will be satisfied with reason, or with mens practices more then their words, may have full resolution to this more usuall then doubtfull question : whether the King, Lords, Commons, Scotts, City, clergy, and officers of the Army, have sought more their own private ends then the publick weale of this nation?</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1647</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 34 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A90443</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P1441</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E416_34</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E421_12</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E464_6</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R203132</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99863204</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99863204</idno>
            <idno type="VID">161366</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A90443)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 161366)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 66:E416[34]; 66:E421[12]; 74:E464[6])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The people and souldiers observations, on the Scotch message to the Parliament, concerning the King; 5. of November 1647. By the scope whereof, all who will be satisfied with reason, or with mens practices more then their words, may have full resolution to this more usuall then doubtfull question : whether the King, Lords, Commons, Scotts, City, clergy, and officers of the Army, have sought more their own private ends then the publick weale of this nation?</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>16 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1647]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Place of publication from Wing.</note>
                  <note>Wing gives publication date as 1648, but Thomason received his copy in 1647.</note>
                  <note>A reprinting of and reply to: A message to both Houses of Parliament, for a personall treaty with the King, (and his Majesty to come to London,) or treat at Hampton-Court.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: significant print show-through.</note>
                  <note>Annotations on Thomason copies: "Nouemb. 28. 1647" (E.416[34]); "This is ye paper mentioned in ye diurnall 27 Decemb." (E.421[12]); "Sept: 15. 1648" (E.464[6]).</note>
                  <note>Reproductions of the originals in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Charles --  I, --  King of England, 1600-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>England and Wales. --  Parliament --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Message to both Houses of Parliament, for a personall treaty with the King, (and his Majesty to come to London,) or treat at Hampton-Court --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Politics and government --  1642-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Civil War, 1642-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:161366:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>THE PEOPLE AND SOVLDIERS OBSERVATIONS, ON THE SCOTCH MESSAGE TO THE PARLIAMENT, CONCERN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the <hi>KING;</hi> 5. of November 1647.</head>
            <head type="sub">By the ſcope whereof, all who will be ſatisfied with Reaſon, or with mens practices more then their words, may have full reſolution to this more uſuall then doubtfull Queſtion: <hi>Whether the King, Lords, Commons, Scotts, City, Clergy, and Officers of the Army, have ſought more their own private ends then the publick weale of this Nation?</hi>
            </head>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="message">
                        <head>The words of the Meſſage here follow in order.</head>
                        <opener>
                           <salute>Right Honourable,</salute>
                        </opener>
                        <p>
                           <hi>AS upon the removal of his</hi> Majeſty <hi>from</hi> Holdenby, <hi>againſt his will, by a party of the Army under the command of Sir</hi> Shomas Fairfax, <hi>we expreſſed our ſenſe and the reſentment of the Kingdome of</hi> Scotland <hi>of that violent action, ſo the Committee of Eſtates of the Parliament of</hi> Scotland, <hi>finding that his</hi> Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty <hi>is ſtill kept within the power of that Army, thought themſelves obliged to indeavour to know the certainty of His condition, in obedience to his commands, wee have applied our ſelves to His</hi> Majeſty, <hi>that from himſelfe we might know the truth there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, who was pleaſed to ſhew us his uſage, ever ſince he came from</hi> New-caſtle, <hi>but for his preſent condition he really confeſſeth he cannot, but referres us to know it, from the two Houſes of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and the Army.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <p>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:161366:2"/>
Dear Brethren (wee may well ſay) here yee expreſſe (in very patheticall words) the tenderneſſe of our affections to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards this forlorne ſucceſſour of all the numerous race of your tyrannicall Kings, of which many not being a tenth part ſo wicked as this, yee have rewarded otherwiſe; it is a wonder that ſuch high minded people as ye, can ſo underva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lue your ſelves, as ſtill and alwaies to ſtoop your ſtiffe necks, rather to the heavy manarchiall yoake of cruell tyrants, then to pitty and free both your ſelves and your poſterities, from all kind of ſlavery and miſery, having now a fairer occaſion and more precious opportunity, then ever yee had hereto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, or may poſſibly ever have hereafter.</p>
            <p>If yee were as juſt in your practices, as yee are wiſe in your conceits, yee would have long a-goe either alone, when he was under your power, or ſince, by advice and aſſiſtance of our Parliament and Army, rather called him to a ſtrict ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, impeached him of moſt high treaſon, and arraigned him for all his great abominations, oppreſſions, murthers, and deſtructions throughout all theſe three bleeding Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons (even from the death of his Father, untill he was catch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the midſt of his ſins, ripe enough for the ſickle of Gods judgements) then anywiſe to be ſo zealouſly affected, and tender hearted concerning his uſage ſince yee delivered him at <hi>New-Caſtle,</hi> and how he hath learned the leſſon of obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to the Armies commands, now after he hath forfeited his authority, and loſt his tyrannicall ſting.</p>
            <p>Certainly, it may well be deemed by his uſuall double-dealing, that if he had you once more under his arbitrary power, as the Army hath juſtly both taken and kept him all this time, untill now that he was conveied away to act more miſchief; he would ſo remember your taking up armes (though in your owne defence) againſt him and his forces both at home and here, for all that is come and gone, and notwithſtanding all your kindneſſe and tender
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:161366:2"/>care now of him, he would teach you perfectly to know what he meaned and intended, when he both proclaimed you all Rebels and Traitors, and levied ſuch ſtrong forces by Sea and Land againſt you; and all for your refuſing his popiſh Service-book.</p>
            <p>But it ſeemeth, that yee (eſpecially unto whom he hath either given or promiſed great offices and honourable titles) have ſo well learned ſome new court leſſons, that yee have quite forgotten your good old faſhions, even to eſteem of Kings as of other mortall men, and not to idolize them, nor hide their haynous faults, as moſt of our vulgar fort havetoo long fooliſhly done, even to our gaeat griefe, and both their and our vexation, yea, yee had rather like the men of <hi>Lyſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ra,</hi> who in their blind and ſuperſticious zealo, both called <hi>Barnabas Jupiter,</hi> and <hi>Paul Mercurius,</hi> and would have offered ſacrifice to them, if thoſe Appoſtles had not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terrupted them, then anywiſe like diſcreet men, who ſhould diſeerne between thoſe who ought to be honoured and reſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected, and ſuch as deſerve to be tryed and puniſhed.</p>
            <p>Have yee ſo ſoon forgotten how he made the beſt and greateſt of you, not only know the newes, but feel the ſmart, that his little finger was heavier then his Fathers loynes (wereof too many of us want not enough of ſuch experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence alſo, and that by all kind of oruell oppreſſions, in things both ſpirituall and temporall; heavy taxations, perſecuti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and neither hearing nor regarding petitions, but impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoning, baniſhing, exiling yea, and intending to execute your own grand Commiſſioner, whom he hath ſince prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to be your Chancella<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> (upon what termes they two beſt know) never obſerving any agreement, performing any promiſe, nor regarding either ſaith, truth or juſtice more to you then us, but all in hypociſie, deceit, and King-craft, (al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies acting and proſecuting what his Father deviſed and contrived) even by plotting, conſpiring, and all ſort of <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chivelian</hi>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:161366:3"/>dealing, to extirpate, root-out, undermine, and deſtroy as well all kind of goodneſs, faithfulneſs and juſtice, as good peaceable and true hearted people.</p>
            <p>A few inſtances may ſuffice, becauſe not only the ſight of a great parte thereof is ſtill ſo cleare before our eyes, but the ſmart of all, is yet ſo recent and freſh in our memories and apprehenſions, howſoever ye like unthrifty Schollers, have rubbed and worn both all the remembrance of your leſſons, &amp; marks of your ſtripes, out of your minds, &amp; from off your backs, with high titles, great offices, new promiſes, and lof<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty hopes: Have yee likewiſe rubbed out of your memories, all his cheating of you (by meanes of <hi>Henderſon</hi> the great, at firſt one of your high <hi>Prieſts,</hi> and next one of his Chaplins) of all his royall performance of that agreement which he made wtth you at <hi>Dunce-law,</hi> and you; ſurrendring to him of <hi>Edenburgh-Caſtle,</hi> and his planting therein both a number of our Country <hi>Papiſts<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> and aboundance of our ammunition, by which inſtruments and meanes, he made many of you ſo ſight, ſob, weep and groane (yea and leave <hi>Edenburgh</hi> town) that yee were ready to curſe, both the day of that a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greement, and the birth-day of all thoſe that had any hand in it: Have ye alſo forgotten how (by his means) our Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try <hi>Papiſts</hi> blew up with a train of gunpowder, a Caſtle full of your <hi>Nobility, gentry and Ladies,</hi> in the aire; neare <hi>Barwick</hi> where your <hi>Generall</hi> narrowly eſcaped? And do ye not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member how in your laſt Parliament when he was preſent, that the one day he gave you (as it were, a purſe full of gold and jewels in the one hand, even all and whatſoever yee de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired, or at leaſt required, but in the other hand a <hi>Scottiſh-dagger,</hi> whereby he would have killed and devoured you all before yee was aware? For at his own palace did he not ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>point a dozen to kill each one a man at one appointed hour of your meeting, even a dozen of the chiefeſt of you, whom he thought were his greateſt oppoſers, or moſt able, and poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticke, to croſſe his popiſh and bloudy deſignes?</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:161366:3"/>
Was not this bloodie attempt ſo contrived and ordered, that your Generall was the firſt man to have been thus trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cherouſly ſtobed, and cowardly murthered, and then as his Majeſtie conceved any of you oppoſit to him in your places to have proceded againſt you, and all the reſt as his Majeſtie ſhould bee Gratiouſly pleaſed; even as wee ſee Butchers doe with their fat Oxen: But it pleaſed God, both to diſcover and prevent that plot for your good, if yee have ſo much grace as to make a happy uſe thereof, now in your great need; which (as ſome of our Country-men report) was on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly diſcovered by meanes of him, who was imployed to kill your Generall: And alſo of the like plot at that ſame time to have beene here againſt ſome of our Parliament mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, which wee thankfully remember was prevented by ſome of your Nation, howbeit it tooke, ſuch a wofull ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect in <hi>Ireland,</hi> that it ſtill continueth almoſt to the deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on thereof, beſides a greater multitude of other enormi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, plots, cruelties and oppreſſions, then either tongue or pen can expreſſe.</p>
            <p>Meſſ.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Both Houſes (by many profeſſions and ingagements) have de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared to the Kingdome of</hi> Scotland, <hi>that they would take care of the preſervation of his perſon, his juſt power and greatneſſe, (which both Kingdomes have ſworn not to diminiſh) and the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament of</hi> Scotland <hi>upon the Kings going to</hi> Holdenby, <hi>did de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare againſt all harme, prejudiee, injury, or violence to be done to his royall perſon, Therefore in purſuance of the truſt commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to us, wee make this addreſſe to the Honourable Houſes, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving it needleſſe to apply our ſelves to the Army, who wee ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe are and ought to be under their command, deſiring to know from them the certainty of his Majeſties condition: And the ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther that wee are informed, their are intentions in the Army of the removing him from</hi> Hampton-Court.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:161366:4"/>
               <hi>Obſerv.</hi> Whatſoever our Parliament hath declared to the Kingdome of Scotland, for taking care of the Kings perſon, it is in reference to that enſnaring covenant, which yee (by meanes of your deceitfull Clergy) faſtened upon our corrupt Commiſſioners, when they agreed with you to aſſiſt our for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and ſo they unjuſtly upon our Parliament, and the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament upon the whole Nation; and yet in the Covenant by vertue of that agreement (wee ſuppoſe) there is no abſolute promiſe nor oath to preſerve the Kings perſon, power nor greatneſſe, whether he be a King or a tyrant, diſcharge his du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, or betray his truſt; but only a conditionall promiſe and vow of his preſervation, whil'ſt he ſheweth his fidelity by his activity in the defence of our juſt Lawes and Liberties, and no otherwiſe: which if hee ever did ſince that time, but rather more cruelly &amp; tyrannically uſed his Norman power then ever hee did, wee even refer the judgement thereof to God, the world and your owne conſciences.</p>
            <p>But your Parliament and Nation in ſtead of trying him according to Law and juſtice, declare againſt all harme, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judice, injury or violence, to bee done to his Majeſties royall perſon; as if he had been borne a Law-leſs Libertine, even to doe all kind of miſchief to thouſands, ten thouſands and hundreds of thouſands; and yet never be ſo much as once queſtioned himſelfe, or ſcarce thoſe who aſſiſted him.</p>
            <p>If he urged, threatened and raiſed cruell warres againſt you, for refuſing that maſſe-booke, which hee undertoke (with all the rable of Popery) to plant amongſt both you and us, in that his moſt vile and flatering <hi>Letter to the Pope,</hi> yet extant in print: why then doe not yee deal with him, as the only party with whom yee have to doe, and not trouble us with your Covenant, Reformation nor religion (whether it bee good or bad) more then wee trouble you with ours; as yee did both ingeniouſly propheſs and faithfully promiſe, in your declaration for aſſiſting our Parliament and Nation. Reaſ. 6.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:161366:4"/>
Have yee likwiſe forgotten, what love and reſpect all of us (whom yee now moſt cruelly and unjuſtly both hate, and ſtir up our enimies to perſecute) did beare unto you, not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly by our former Parliament, who abſolutly refuſed him all kind of aide and aſſiſtance to come againſt you, but likewiſe, by our unanimous chuſing rather to undergo his higheſt diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſure (according to our free and rationall principles) then to take up armes to aſſiſt him in that unjuſt quarell.</p>
            <p>Beſids, in that Declaration, yee acknowledge that we have been your neareſt and deareſt freinds, being willing &amp; ready to help and aſſiſt you in all your ſtraits and extremities: and therfore if ye either ſuffer or cauſe us to ſink in ſuch miſeries ye proteſt there; <hi>that ye not only betray our ſafety but your own</hi> (as ſtanding &amp; falling together) &amp; ſo ye there conclude, <hi>that yee will doe to</hi> us herein <hi>as yee would bee done unto:</hi> and in di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers of your other Remonſtrances and Declarations, yee thankfully remember great aide and aſſiſtance which ye have receved of us; chiefly, at the expelling of the French out of your Nation in the dayes of your Queene Regent, which fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours yee vow and Imprecate never to forget.</p>
            <p>Now, ſeeing yee thus confeſſe, profeſſe, proteſt and promiſe, both to our greate credite and your owne greate comfort, what Neighbourly kindneſſes yee have received of us, and what reſpect therfore yee owe unto us: whence then cometh this great change, both of your affections, reſoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, words and actions? cannot yee reſt contented with your own miſery and ſlavery, and not like Satan to tempt or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlave others? For it ſeemeth to us, that yee love ſuch unwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy conditions better then either your lives or eſtates, and have almoſt theſe nine yeares both adventured the one and conſumed the other, in pretending to fight againſt a a cruell tyrant, and yet all this time intending to fight for a cruell tyrant (as yee too well taught our deceitfull Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment) and that yee and your poſterity may be ſtill hence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forth,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:161366:5"/>as yee have been alwayes heretofore, not only his and his prediceſſours ſlaves, but as hee uſeth you, ſo yee may ſtil uſe (or rather abuſe and enſlave) all the poore people under you, after that lamentable and baſe example of France.</p>
            <p>Doubtleſs, yee are a hundred-fould worſe (as well in this reſpect as in many others) then the Iſralits in the daies of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muel, who luſted to have a King like other Nations; for they not yet feeling the evills and inconveniences which would accompany a King, though they had ſufficient notice given them thereof by the Prophet; but yee have enough of ſuch greevous and lamentable experience already your ſelves, beſides what yee (both as eye and eare witneſſes) well know both we and Ireland have; even that hee (who is now your beſt beloved Country man) hath moſt cruelly exerciſed (at leaſt) all the grevous oppreſſions which Samuell fore-tould of King Saul; and therefore, except hee repent, as God gave that wicked King in his anger to Iſraell, and tooke him away in his wrath; ſo doubtleſſe he gave; and will take your King, whom yee ſtill both reſpect and endevour to excuſe and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend in all his moſt hainous Sins, Abominations, Murthers, Injuſtices, Tyranies and oppreſſions; far exceeding either Saul, Jeroboam, Ahab, Ahaz, or Ammon, if not all of them.</p>
            <p>Yet notwithſtanding all this, yee (like wiſe merchants who take and keep all advantages againſt unſkilfull cuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers) ſtill hould ſo faſt and ſtick ſo cloſſe to your bargain, which yee made with our corrupt Parliament, when yee ſaw them in ſuch a ſtraight, that they were in feare and danger of both their lives and eſtates, by his wicked meanes, and their owne unjuſt dealings; and that even beſides your hyre and wages, yee (by the device, meanes and aſſiſtance of the chief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt incendiaries of all theſe bloodie warres, even your ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, covetous and pernitious Clergy, confederating with ours) moſt unjuſtly procured your deceitfull Covenant to
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:161366:5"/>be both taken by our Parliament, and forced upon the whole Nation; and conſequently your humane religion, under the colour of reformation; though it paſſeth the limits and bounds of all their Commiſſions or abilities; ſeing thereunto they never had the conſent of the free people of this Nation who both chuſed and truſted them; yea and are like to bee called to an exact and ſtrict account by them, both for theſe and many hundreds more of other wrongs, treacheries and acts of Injuſtice; eſpecially, in that they would not call him to an account for all his tirranny and wickedneſſe, exerciſed over the free people of this Nation, ſince the begining of his Raigne, nor deale with him according to his deſerts; neither before theſe warres began, nor when they began, nor yet ever ſince they have beene, (though they might often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times) and ſo to haue prevented both the effuſion of much blood and the deſtruction &amp; waſting of manifold treaſures and eſtates:</p>
            <p>And howſoever yee Commiſſionars, in purſuance of the truſt commited to you, by thoſe that ſent you, will make your adreſſe only to our Parliament, conceiving it nedleſſe to apply your ſelves to the army, who ye ſuppoſe are and ought to bee under the Parliaments command; yet yee are to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider, that the Parliament are but the Commons of Englands ſervants, as well as the Army; as yee know Prophets and Prieſts of ould, or Biſhops and Miniſters of late, are not ſupe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riours to Kings (in temporall matters at leaſt) though they be imployed by the people, to put the Croun on their heads, and take their Oaths for the faithfull diſcharging of their Offices; yea and in regard our Parliament have run them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves over head and eares into ſo manifould gulfes of injuſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ice, that they nither deſerve the title nor reſpect which is due to a Juſt, diſcreete, faithfull and carefull Parliament: and and therefore they now lye (as it were) proſtrate on their knees, as well at the mercie of the Commons of England
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:161366:6"/>as your good King doth at this preſent; ſo that all their ſub<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tile propoſitions &amp; treaties with him, nor yet the City, Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy, nor corrupt Officers of the Army to help them, will nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther availe nor prevent the fearfull Interrogatories, which poſſibly and ſpeedily may be demanded of either; then ye will have ocaſion to take up ſuch a mourning and lamentati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on for your good King, who hath ſo advanced your glorious Reformation, as both <hi>Jerem. the Prophet, and all Judah with the ſinging women, did for the death of good King Joſiah, in the Valley of Megiddo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Meſſ. <hi>The Kingdome af Scotland finding that their ſtabili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and happineſſe doth ſo much depend upon the ſafety and preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of his Majeſties royall perſon, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obſer.</hi> Now, yee having both expreſſed your owne fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent deſires and ſincere affections towards your good King, have alſo endevoured to make our Parliament and Nation doe the like: yee come in the third place to ſhew the cauſe of all this great buſineſſe; namly, whereupon your ſtability and happyneſs doth ſo much depend; which yee attribute to <hi>The ſafety and preſervation of his Majeſties royall perſon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is a wonder, that yee ſhould either bee ſo ignorant or void of ſhame, as to expreſſe ſo impudently and evidently ſuch vile untruths, flatteries and contrarieties, even againſt both your owne experiences, underſtandings and conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, chiefly in theſe late and ſad dayes, both of your affliction and ours, which yee well know hath been all by his meanes; being a moſt cruell ſcourge to plague both you and us for all our hainous ſins, as Nebucadnezar was in puniſhing Iſraell for theirs: and therefore yee (upon that ſandy ground of your owne humours and conceits,) doe run the hazzard of the following reſolution.</p>
            <p>Meſſ. <hi>And being reſolved that no alteration of affaires ſhall ever ſeparate them from that duty allegiance they ow unto him, nor from their conſtant reſolvtions to live in all loyalty and obedience
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:161366:6"/>under his government, have often ſhewne their earneſt deſires, and contributed their utmoſt endevours, towards the compoſure of theſe unhappy differences.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ob.</hi> Here yee would ſay, if diſſimulation would permit you, no wickedneſſe, oppreſſion nor tyranny that he and all his helliſh Cavaliers, bloudy papiſts, prophane Countiers, flattering favorits, and domineering Biſhops, can commit, ſhall ever ſeparate you from the performance of that duty of Allegiance ye owe unto him, and conſtant reſoluſion yee have to live in all loyalty and obedience under his govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and that yee have been very active towards the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſure of theſe unhappy differences.</p>
            <p>All which words may perhaps feed the fancy of the ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple and ignorant multitude, who are alwaies ready to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luded by ſuch meanes, but they will never ſavour nor ſmell of any goodneſſe, juſtice, nor integrity to any impartiall diſcreet, or judicious men: becauſe they proceed either of very weake or corrupt principles, of a ſlaviſh diſpoſition, or blind affection, without either ſenſe, reaſon, due, or true ſatisfaction, though yee make him (as it were) your joy and your Crowne</p>
            <p>Meſſ. <hi>And the Houſes of Parliament having by their Votes of the 26th. of</hi> Oct. <hi>laſt, intimated to us their reſoluſions to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply themſelves to his Majeſty, and that they are preparing Propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions to be tendred to him; Wee doe deſire that they may be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedited and communicated to us; that according to our many en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagements and relations there may be ſtill a conjunction of coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cels, in thoſe things that are for the common peace, ond joynt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſts of both Kingdomes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>And for the better aſſerting of them, for clearing his Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties doubts, and for the giving, and receiving muturall ſatisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction: Wee doe deſire (in the name of the Kingdome of Scotland) that there may be a perſonall Treaty with the King, as the beſt and redieſt meanes to obtaine the joynt deſires of both Kingdoms;
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:161366:7"/>And for that effect, that the King may bee invited to come to London, with that honour, freedom, and reſpect due to his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty, or (at leaſt) remaine at Hampton-Court, and not under the power and conſtraint of Souldiers, where both Kingdomes may make their free applications to him, without any danger of ſuch ſtop, or affront as hath been alredy commited againſt a Commiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oner of Scotland: and for which no reparation hath bin made, and that his Majeſtie bee no more carried about with the Army at their pleaſures. &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Here is ſtill a continued courſe of great buſineſſes (as well now after, as it was throughout all the warres) of addreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of Parliaments and ſtates, as well <hi>Engliſh</hi> as <hi>Scots,</hi> by Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions to be tendred to him, with all expedition, and communicated to you for unity and peace ſake; as if judges ſhould preſent petitions, and offer conditions<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> of peace unto ſuch malefactors as ſtand guilty at their Bar.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Ob. And for the better &amp;c.</hi> Here is a great deale of ſtuffe to little purpoſe, truly it is a pitty yee were not as diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creet as yee would appear to be; by meanes of your Prieſtly generation, yee are ſtill of ſuch a ſtrange diſpoſition, that al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though yee doe reſort to all Nations your ſelves, yet yee will permit none to dwell among you, who are more able or bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter principled then your ſelves, and might poſſibly inſtruct you, both in ſpirituall and temporall freedomes, better then all your teachers and Lawyers: witneſſe your hard uſage from time to time, (chiefly in the firſt three yeares of your late troubles) what numbers of our people reſorted amongſt you, thinking there had been ſome hopes to have made you a free-principled, diſcreet and abſolute free people, and not to be carried away neither by wicked Kings, nor time-ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Prieſts; but ſome of our people, as well as your owne, had impriſoning inſtead of reaſoning, and both of them bad entertainment for endeavouring your good.</p>
            <p>And concerning the Kings coming to <hi>London,</hi> doe yee
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:161366:7"/>not know, he may come thither, with that honour, freedome and reſpect which is due unto him, and yet with little con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent either to himſelfe or to you?</p>
            <p>Yee make ſo much of a diſſembling <hi>Abſolon,</hi> a cruell mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derer, and bloudy tyrant, as wee have great cauſe to be jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous, that yee have left your firſt love which yee appeared to have, and that yee have not ſuch a meaſure of diſcretion as to diſcerne between good and evill, nor between thoſe that laſh, whip and ſcourge you, yea, and both makes you gather ſtraw, and performe your whole taſk of bricks too; and thoſe who tell you the truth for your preſent and future good, yee both perſecute even with a deadly hatrered, and indeavour more to force your Religion by the ſword, then anywiſe to convince by the word; ſo that if neither ſword nor peſtilence can humble you, God hath both famine and other judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments which doubtleſſe will doe it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Meſſ. Theſe we conceive to be the moſt probable and effectuall meanes for attaining a happy peace, ſettling of Religion, restoring his Majesty to his just Rights, and continuing, and strengthen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a good understanding betwixt theſe Kingdomes, which are most earnestly deſired by the Kingdome of Scotland, and ſhall bee constantly and faithfully endevoured by &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Obſ. If ye conceive that theſe corrupt courſes, which ſo tend to juſtifie the wicked and condeme the juſt, are the moſt probable &amp; effectuall meanes, for obtaining theſe your ends; yea, and being ſo contrary to your juſt proteſtations againſt his proclaimations, &amp; your takeing up armes againſt his for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces; wee deſire that yee would either ſhew how this can bee poſſible; or how this your great and ſuddain change cometh, or elſe, acknowledge your errour herein; ſeeing there is nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther any beginning nor appearance of repentance in him, notwithſtanding all his deceitfull Proteſtations and bloudy warres in all the three Nations: otherwiſe, ye will both in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curre blame, and come ſhort of obtaining a happy peace,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:161366:8"/>reſtoring him to his juſt rights, and both continuing and ſtrengthening a good underſtanding between theſe Nations, though it be never ſo much both deſired by you and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavoured by your Commiſſioners in your behalfe.</p>
            <p>But ſuppoſing yee cannot ſhew how ſuch a thing is poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, we will endeavour therefore to ſhew you, how farre yee have both changed your minds, &amp; in our apprehenſions, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generated from the perfect rules of equity and juſtice in two years time, that ye may learn to lay a more ſolid founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion where upon to build your ſtability &amp; happines, then on the ſandy foundation of the ſafety &amp; preſervation of a wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed mans perſon, though of never ſo great a majeſty &amp; <hi>royalty</hi> (as yee ſay) and by ſuch corrupt flattering and deceit full meanes, yea, and unjuſt tearmes and titles, to juſtifie and protect him in all his wickednes, both againſt your ſelves and us: wee ſend you back againe, to read and conſider once more, your own generall aſſemblies Remonſtrance, publiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to the view of the world, <hi>June</hi> 12. 1645.</p>
            <p>Chiefly <hi>page</hi> 3. line 16, 17, 18, 19. and <hi>page</hi> 5. <hi>line</hi> 14, 15, 16, 17, 18, 19, 20, 21, 22, 23. and <hi>page</hi> 6. <hi>
                  <abbr>l.</abbr>
               </hi> 19, 20, 21, 22. The words are theſe;</p>
            <p>
               <hi>When wee call to mind, that God accepteth not the perſons of men, and that the greateſt are not to be winked at in their ſinnes; wee make bold to warne your Majeſty freely, that the guilt which cleaveth faſt to your Majeſty, and to your Throne is ſuch, as (what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever flattering preachers or unfaithfull councellers may ſay to the contrary) if not timely prevented, cannot but involve your ſelfe and your poſterity under the wrath of the ever-living God, for your being guilty of the ſhedding of the bloud of many thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands of your Majeſties beſt ſubjects, and for what other cauſes your Majeſty is moſt conſcious, and may beſt judge and ſearch your own conſcience<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now having paraleld your preſent practices with your former judgements, even of late dayes, whereof at firſt wee eſteemed more highly, then either then or ſince, howbeit it
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:161366:8"/>doth now clearly appear, that ye have not been ſound at all howſoever wee as all Chriſtians ought to take every thing' in the beſt or moſt charitable ſenſe, untill time diſcover mens intentions by their actions, according to our <hi>Saviours</hi> rule, <hi>to know the Tree by the fruit;</hi> for inſtance, it appears plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to us now, even by your practices ever ſince, that in your little Book called <hi>Your lawfulneſſe of comming into Eng! a ad, Reaſ.</hi> 6th. Yee have either a bloudy or (at the beſt) a compulſive intention, to root out, or at leaſt to compell all of what ſoever degree, eſtate or condition, to be one with you in <hi>Religion,</hi> by which unjuſt reſolutions, do ye not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume above what is meet, and even uſurp the worke both of Gods word and Spirit?</p>
            <p>If this kind of dealing, be any-wiſe a doing as yee would be done unto, we referre it both to your afore-ſaid declarati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an, and to your owne conſciences; for if yee would not bee pleaſed, that any perſon or ſtate ſhould urge and beat you from your Religion, why then dare yee preſume to urge or beate either us from ours, or any others from theirs; but ſtill to doe as yee would be done unto, for whatſoever meaſure ye give, the like ye ſhall receive.</p>
            <p>And have yee forgoten, is it ſo out of your minds, that yee began all theſe bloody warres, againſt your good King, in the very ſame quarrell? was it not becauſe it was his Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties Royall and gracious pleaſure, to compell you to ſerve God by his Biſhopes and Popiſh booke, otherwiſe then yee were perſwaded, or at leaſt accuſtomed? And if ſo (which ye cannot yet deny, becauſe it can be ſo aboundantly proved) why then will yee be ſo arrogant and wicked, as ſtill to proſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute ſuch an un-godly attempt, and perſecute honeſt and peaceable people? but rather to learne of <hi>Chriſt, to hee meeke, humble and lowly,</hi> endevouring alwayes to convince by the <hi>word,</hi> but never to force by the ſword.</p>
            <p>Again, it cannot be denied, but even thankfully remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:161366:9"/>that ye not only lent us your helping hand, even a pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erfull army, whereby yee forced a Parliament to be called a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong us, when our King made it no leſſe then treaſon to mention a Parliament (being then in the higheſt of his nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man tyranny and malice againſt our birth-rights and liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties) but likewiſe, yee continued your army a whole yeare with us, untill yee ſet us in a right Parliamentary poſture; and ſaw both wicked men puniſhed, and juſt men advanced before yee departed, yea and yee went all away with as great honour, credit and reſpect as (we ſuppoſe) ſuch a great army in any forraigne Nation ever did.</p>
            <p>Upon which ground, and that yee have been alwaies eſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emed a valiant people, and an unconquered Nation howſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever yee be in bondage to your Kings) and did carry your ſelves wiſely in all the particulars of your owne defence a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Kings power and forces, we called you into our Nation with an army to help and aſſiſt us againſt the King; and in the firſt place yee took in New-<hi>Caſtle</hi> againe from his forces, and ſent us Coles both of your owne and from thence, for our moneyes; when many had begun to burne bed-ſteeds and tables above the ſpace of too yeares, for want thereof:</p>
            <p>But herein was your failing, yee began and ran well but who did let you that ye would not goe on to the end of your races, why would ye not be as carefull to aſſiſt our forces and diſcharge your owne duties in all other places and ſervices ſince, as ye were to exact your arreares, and ſo to have made a ſpeedier end of theſe warres.</p>
            <p>Howſoever, upon this view of mutuall duties and favours thus given and received; it is our earneſt deſire, for a better union betwen us, then either ſuch a Covenant or kind of religion can make, that there may bee no further purſuance of us, in a coercive way unto either, more then we indevour againſt you in what we profeſſe or practice, but that LOVE, which is the greateſt Commandement of all, may begin and encreaſe again betwen us as brethren, friends and neighbours, &amp; ſo continue throughout all generations.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
